<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Balaams better wish delivered in a sermon / by William Rose.</title>
            <author>Rose, William, fl. 1647-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09007982</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09007982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42199</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42199)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1293:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Balaams better wish delivered in a sermon / by William Rose.</title>
                  <author>Rose, William, fl. 1647-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.L. for Samuel Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XXIII, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42199:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42199:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BALAAMS BETTER WISH:</p>
            <p>Delivered in a SERMON BY WILLIAM ROSE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 14.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The wicked ſhall be driven away in his wickedneſſe, but the righteous hath hope in his end.</p>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>MAY 8. 1647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Have peruſed this fruitfull, and profitable Sermon, on <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.10. and judge it worthy to be printed and publiſhed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JOHN DOWNAME</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. L.</hi> for SAMUEL MAN, at the ſigne of the SWAN in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42199:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42199:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT WORSHIPFULL Sir <hi>EDMOND BACON,</hi> Knight and Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſing GOD in a gracious diſpenſation of mercy to lay his hand of viſitation upon me, ſo as I have been diſenabled to that publike function of the Miniſtery, to which I am ſet apart: I boldly adventured on this more publick courſe, willing to give ſome teſtimony of my deſire to do my GOD the beſt ſervice I was able, though with the hazard of mine own repute, being never ſuch as I fear to be a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. May it pleaſe my good GOD to accept of theſe my weak endevours, whoſe glory, and his Churches good be ever my ayme: and may you daigne them a gracious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, for the unweighed cenſures of the many, I paſſe not much. Mine own ſickneſſe firſt pitched me on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and while I conſidered your body ſo enfeebled through infirmities, and your many years, the two moſt certain fore-runners of approching death: it emboldned mee to tender this Dedication; hoping you would willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſuch a wiſh, and make it yours. The ſhip that draws water but at one leak may be repayred, but when it breaks
<pb facs="tcp:42199:3"/>in on all ſides, it threatens ſpeedy wrack: when the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, aged body is become
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lucian.</note> a living ſepulchre, it portends the grave is neer. We are at beſt but of
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Plut. ad Apoll.</note> a days continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: and you by the bleſſing of GOD have lived to the evening of age, to the Sun-ſet of mans life, it is now high time to think on ſleep, and making your bed in the duſt. I am confident, diviner thoughts have long ſince deaded your affections unto the world. Length of days,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pind. Olym. Od. 1.</note> the cleèreſt witneſſes of wiſdom have given you experience of the Wiſemans concluſion, <hi>Vanity of vanities:</hi> and you who in your yonger years have had a care to live well, now make it your chiefe to dye ſo. It is not the thought of your end will draw it neerer, nor the meditation of death will one minute ſhorten your life: if ſo who might not feare a publick <hi>odium,</hi> that ſhould move you to ſuch a thought? For You,
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deus amorem viri quem dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in animos hominum dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter reſudit,</hi> Malm. de reb. geſt. Aug. lib. 4.</note> who by the goodneſſe of GOD have lived ſo generally beloved, cannot dye but much lamented, though there be neyther ſolemne Funerall to rayſe the pomp, nor mourning women,
<note n="e" place="margin">Horat. de art. Poet.</note> 
               <hi>ut quae conductae plorent in funere:</hi> Your endeared friends, the poor whoſe wants have been by You relieved, and widows will make lamentation. In that deſires cannot prolong your days on earth, here ſhall be my <hi>Amen.</hi> When the ſet period of your life is come, may you lye down in comfort, rest in peace, ariſe to glory, be happy to eternity. <hi>So prays</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worths true honourer and humble ſervant in Chriſt, <hi>William Roſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42199:3"/>
            <head>BALAAM'S <hi>better Wiſh.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 23.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Let mee dye the death of the righteous, and let my laſt end be like his.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He LORD being now about to ſettle <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the lot of their inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, which he had entayled upon them by promiſe to their father <hi>Abraham;</hi> their Prince, and Prieſt, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> for tempting the LORD at <hi>Meribah:</hi> and the whole number of the men of ſtrength for their infidelity muſt not take poſſeſſion: ſo he wears them out by long journeys for forty yeers in the Wilderneſſe, and conſumes them by fatall wars, while they were waſted. Yet to make his word good to their poſterity, hee drived out and deſtroys the <hi>Amorites</hi> before, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hon</hi> and then King, with <hi>Og</hi> the King of <hi>Baſhan:</hi> their army coaſting about the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, did now verge upon the borders of <hi>Moab. Balaac</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomwhat ſurpriſed with feare, as ſucceſſe ſtrikes dread into the hearts of adverſaries, caſts about to ſecure himſelf. Poore man had he been quiet, he might have been ſecure, but his feare which made him forecaſt to prevent, might betray him to a future ruine. The LORD had not ſaid it. <hi>Iſrael</hi> had no commiſſion ſigned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moab:</hi> but if he will oppoſe himſelf an enemy to them, he may juſtly provoke GOD, and them againſt him. Hee ſends to the <hi>Midianites,</hi> with whom hee was inleague to conſult for their future ſafety. Who together ſent Elders with the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of <hi>Balaac</hi> to <hi>Balaam,</hi> on whom they ſo doted, as if he had commanded the power of Heaven, and could curſe and bleſſe whom he pleaſed. Fooliſh thoughts, the mannage, and order of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42199:4"/>men and their affairs is from no other but from the wiſdom, and order of an eternall providence: who giveth victory to ſome, and layeth the honours of other in the duſt. Who is pleaſed to reveal the purpoſe of his proceedings to particular men, which neither yet are principalls in the ſucceſſe, nor any way carry on the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, though he gives them to foreknow the event. To <hi>Balaam,</hi> GOD gives to foreſee the happy and flouriſhing eſtate of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the grace of divine protection, and their ſucceſſe ordered by Heaven, which cauſed him to break forth into this patheticall peroration. <hi>Let me dye, &amp;c.</hi> The wicked man (as wicked men may have) had good words in his mouth, the Wizz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd had a good wiſh, I dare joyn with him in his prayer, praying it may be with a better ſpirit and affection. My hearty deſire to Heaven ſhall be, when I ſhall have accompliſhed as an hireling my dayes, and ſhall return unto my duſt. I may dye the death of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: in the mean time the LORD grant mee the guidance of his grace, I may ſo live, that my laſt end may be like his. The text preſents us with <hi>Balaams</hi> wiſh concerning his end of this preſent life, and the happineſſe of his future being. When we ſhall have premiſed ſomthing of this <hi>Balaam,</hi> what hee was, and a word or two of the phreſe of ſpeech, wee ſhall fall upon theſe three mayn quaeries of the text. 1 Who is the righteous man? 2. What is the difference between the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the wicked? 3 The ultimate end of either, which will fully diſcover unto us the reaſon, and cauſe of this his deſire.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To derive his pedegree, to deſcribe his countrey, to deſcant on his name were but a dry diſcourſe, which would have more of pomp then weight, more bulk then ſubſtance. I ſhall onely touch at his condition to term this; <hi>Balnam</hi> a Prophet is a better chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter then the Scripture yields him, which entitles him at beſt but a Divinour, a term admitting a worſe ſenſe. The <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſay be had been a Prophet, but the ambition of preferment loſt him the honour of prophecie, and hee wannow onely a Divinour: and ſo they apply to him that Proverbe. <hi>The Camell ſeeking horns loſt her eares:</hi> the Cloſſe ſays in plain terms he was a Magitian, and did foretell things by the miniſtery of the Devill. That hee ſpake here Prophetically it cannot be denied, but that was by an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42199:4"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dispenſative contigii illi ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo non pro me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito ſed pro te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</hi> Bal. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em. in eſ.</note> diſpenſation for the preſent, which proves him no more a Prophet then the act of ſpeech did prove his Aſſe a man though once he ſpake more reaſon then his maſter. Nor does it conclude him ſuch that GOD ordinarily revealed himſelf unto him, and put words into his mouth, who may, and doth make known his truth by
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prophetae dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monum nonnun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam vera di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt quae tamen non propriae ab ipſis, ſed potius à Spiritu San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto profiſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Aquin. 2. 2 ae q. 173. art. 6 conc.</note> wicked men. The phraſe of Scripture may ſeem to put a difference between them who were not, and them who were the Prophets of the LORD. When it ſpeaks of the firſt ſort it ſays, <hi>and the LORD came to</hi> Laban, <hi>and the LORD came to</hi> Abimelek, <hi>and the LORD came to</hi> Balaam. When it ſpeaks of the ſecond ſort it lays. <hi>The word of the LORD came unto them, thus ſayth the LORD the hand of the LORD is upon me,</hi> This may in part fatisfie, but the diſcovery of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſhew him wholly vile. At the firſt time he was lent for by <hi>Balaat,</hi> berefuſes to go, it was well yet hee would not ſtirre ere GOD would figne him his Commiſſion. The King not here reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it is no eaſie matter to ſatisfie fear, and jealouſie) ſends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the ſecond time. Larger proffers are propounded, and the promiſe of great promotion to him
<note n="c" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Who loved the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe,</hi> was a ſharp ſpur to ſet him forth. The Kings coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, Court honour, on his own terms over-weighed his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious affections, and wrought upon his coverous deſires: <hi>to run greedily for reward, Jude</hi> 11. which bee conceals, and it muſt reſt whether yet he LORD will give him leave to go. Did he think him changeable in his counſels? or could he imagine to move GOD by an importunity to abet his iniquity? had his heart been right with GOD as he would pretend he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have tempted him the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond time, after ſo de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r an intimation of his will, and purpoſe: it is no piety to tempt GOD by an importunity to what he is not willing: but when hee gives a flat denyall, it is high temerity there not to ceaſe. May my corrupt affections be everſilent while my ſoul utters it ſelf unto my GOD. Leſt they prompt mee with unjuſt deſires, which may neyther ſtand with his glory, or my good. May a religious feare ever bound my peritions, that GODS grant may be a free act of grace that hee gives mee not, nor permits me in his anger what in his gracious pleaſure hee would deny. <hi>Balaam</hi> would wreſt a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42199:5"/>grant, and go hee ſhall, GOD permits him: but how hee was thereat offended is evident, in that he would rather work a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and open the Aſſes mouth then there ſhould want one to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the maſters madneſſe, and when <hi>Balaam</hi> came thither, what ever his heart was, there was a ſpirit that moved his tongue,
<note n="d" place="margin">Chap. 22.25.</note> and put words into his mouth other then which hee could not utter. Nothing pleaſing unto the King, or which might much implead him upon his promiſe,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Antiq. Jud. lib</hi> 4.6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Joſephus</hi> frames <hi>Balaam</hi> this excuſe to <hi>Balaac.</hi> Thinkeſt thou that it is in us ſo oft as we ſpeak the fates what we will ſay and wherein we will be ſilent, who are inſpired with the Holy Ghoſt: which utters what words and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles it pleaſes, wee not knowing or thinking of them. Who ſo ſoon as he enters into our breaſts, there remayns nothing of ours there. The laſt words muſt be laid hold of, becauſe I perceive them a ſetled opinion in after times, which the ſounder Fathers oppoſed. Some ſay
<note n="f" place="margin">Proem. in Jeſ.</note> (ſays <hi>Baſill</hi>) that the divinely illuminated do propheſie their humane ſoule being ſwallowed up of the Spirit, but it abhorreth from the profeſſed truth, and goodneſſe of the divine preſence to make him a mad man who is inſpired by GOD. And when hee ſhall begin to be filled with divine Oracles, that then he ſhould be out of his own wits.] What is there ſuch an antipathy between a man qualified by the Spirit of GOD, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly endued with thoſe rare and excellent gifts of knowledge, and underſtanding, and between divine inſpirations, that he muſt be wholly emptied of the former, that the latter may be infuſed? Muſt the Oracles of divine wiſdome be uttered by men beſide themſelves? Does the eternall wiſe GOD ſo provide for the ſalvation of his people, that the ſober truths of heavenly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge muſt be preached by mad men? they ſpake not themſelves but <hi>as the Spirit gave them utterance, Acts</hi> 2.4. yet not what they underſtood not.
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prophetia primo &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipaliter in cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione conſiſlit ſecondario au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in loquutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> Aquin. 2. 2. ae. q. 173. art. 1. concl.</note> How is it then a prophecy? I can allow it of <hi>Caiphas</hi> whom yet I will not ſo readily grant to be a Prophet, though as high Prieſt hee ſpake prophetically. Who as hee ſpake not of himſelfe, ſo neither underſtood hee the burden of his Word. His minde meditated on one thing, the Spirit intended another:
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dum crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem necis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petiit redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis gratiam prophetabit.</hi> Greg. Mor. 23.3.</note> hee thirſted for bloud, and thought on murther, while hee prophecied of the grace of our Redeemer. But wee,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42199:5"/>ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>have a ſure word of prophecy as a light ſhining in a darke place,</hi> 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.19. and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an illumination or <hi>manifeſtation of the Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. I read of an Idoll in
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt Rom. qu.</hi> 56. <hi>Carmeata quaſi carens mente.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> who was called <hi>Carmenta,</hi> her Worſhippers <hi>Carmentae,</hi> the deduction of the name is a fit expreſſe of ſuch fool Idolaters. The Devill by objecting phantaſmes may elude the underſtanding, and diſtract the rationall faculties: but the good and wiſe GOD works not ſo. What <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>the Prophet is a fool, the ſpirituall man is mad, Hoſea</hi> 9.7. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> explains it, <hi>that prophecy out of their own hearts, feoliſh Prophets that follow their own ſpirit and have ſeen nothing, Ezek</hi> 13.2, 3. Such Montaniſing mad Enthuſiaſts that pretend to divine inſpirations the World hath known (that I may not ſay this age hath) too many. I grant ſome Prophets might be in an extaſie and rapture at the admiration of divine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations. But there is a
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fuerunt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae in extaſi non in extaſi mentis,</hi> Epiph. l. 2. tom. 1. haer. 48.</note> twofold extaſie.</p>
            <p n="1">1 From the outward and inward ſenſes, the minde temayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the more enlightned, the more the ſoul is abſtracted from ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive objects:
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conticeſcant mihi omnia ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea ſibi ſile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</hi> Aug. Med. c. 37.</note> as ſhe is more full in her devotions: ſo the more free for divine inſpirations.</p>
            <p n="2">2 From the minde it ſelfe when it underſtandeth not,
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non excide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant mente pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae.</hi> Orig. hom. 6. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. 16.</note> ſo never were they in an extaſie: but did utter all things
<note n="n" place="margin">Epiph. ubi ſupra.</note> with firme reaſon and underſtanding, and ſpake from the Holy Spirit with a perfect minde, and body. So that I ground not ſo much on the ſpeech of this wicked man, as his after advice proves him full. Who ſeeing enchantment failed, and divinations could do nothing: <hi>becauſe GOD had beheld no iniquity in</hi> Jacob, <hi>nor perverſneſſe in Iſrael. Numb.</hi> 22.21.
<note n="o" place="margin">Ioſeph. ubi ſupra.</note> counſelled <hi>Balaac</hi> to tempt them by the <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> women to commit fornication. And if the opinion of the Antiquary ſeems too light, it may have allowance from that of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to the Church of <hi>Pergamus, I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt there them that hold the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of</hi> Balaam, <hi>who taught</hi> Balaac <hi>to caſt a ſtumbling block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the children of Iſrael, to eat things ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit fornication,</hi> Revel. 2.14. For which wicked advice of his, when God ſet <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon the revenge of <hi>Midian</hi> this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinour as hee ran for the wages, ſo hee had full paid the reward
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42199:6"/>of iniquity. <hi>They killed</hi> Balaam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Beor <hi>with the ſword. Joſhua</hi> 13.22. where wee will leave him in his unhappy end.</p>
            <p>Though the originall runs in the futuretenſe yet is not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted as a prophecy that ſo it ſhould, but as it is tranſlated in the ſenſe of the optative mood (which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> wanting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe deſires in the future of the Indicative) ſignifying a wiſh or deſire that ſo it might be, To dye is Heavens heavy doom upon the ſons of <hi>Adam.</hi> An unrepealable Statute hath paſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>it is appointed for all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> (without any limitation) <hi>once to dye Heb.</hi> 9.27. Other are the limits and bounds of nature, other are the extraordinary ways of working with the Almighty. He may if he pleaſe diſpenſe with this law, as hee hath done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elijah:</hi> and there ſhall be a more generall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for them which ſhall be found alive at the laſt day. <hi>We ſhall not all dye, but we ſhall all be changed,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. Which change ſhall be anſwering to a death, though without any reall ſeparation of the ſoul from the body. Which I ground</p>
            <p n="1">1 On the term uſed by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Wee ſhall not lye down to ſleep in the duſt, or wee ſhall not dye</hi> as it is rendred, which imports a diſſolution of ſoul, and body.</p>
            <p n="2">2 On that circumſtance of time in which this ſhall be done, <hi>in a moment in the twinkling of an ere,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in an atome,</hi> an unconceivable inſtant of time. Which I take to be an after copy of <hi>Adams</hi> condition, had hee retained his innocency, he had been tranſlated, not knowing death to a bleſſed immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, but he fayling in his obedience, conſiderable not onely as a perſon, but as the nature of mankind, all tranſgreſſed in him.
<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by one man, and in, and by the one ſin of that one man, all man ſin and dyed.</hi> So that as no man can acquit himſelfe from the contagion of his unrighteouſnes, nor yet from the guilt of perſonall practice:
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Samon.</note> So none may expect to be exempted from the penalty due thereunto: no not the righteous man who is now to be conſidered of.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>ſignifies to be right <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.4. <hi>And this was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight in the peoples eyes</hi> it did pleaſe them, or they did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it: ſo the righteous man is hee who is right in the ſight
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42199:6"/>of the LORD, he pleaſes GOD, and hee approves of him: <hi>For the righteous GOD loveth righteouſneſſe, his countenance doth behold the upright, Pſal.</hi> 11.7. Hee looks on him with content, as we eye the things we love with delight.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It ſignifies the perfect man. Whom that wee may the better deſcribe wee muſt lay downe a rule of perfection, according to which wee are to judge of him. GOD being only wiſe, and good, and all perfection, that abſolute <hi>Idea,</hi> muſt be in a
<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 5.48.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity unto him, this conformity wee held by the vertue of the Image of God ſtamped upon us in our creation, ſo long as wee kept that Image undefiled, and undefaced. For the modell of our nature, we were holy and juſt, and good: but ſoon was this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py condition forfeited by our diſobedience, and there followed ſuch diſcraſie in our intellectuall, ſuch diſorder in our practicall faculties; that we could neither know, nor will, nor doe, thoſe things which were of God, who in his gracious goodneſſe that hee might repaire this unhappy loſſe, gave us his Law a cleere <hi>manifeſto</hi> of his
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> perfect will, that in our obedience thereunto, we might recover our holineſſe, and reforme our lapſed nature by a rule of righteouſneſſe: a Directory for the ordering of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life to futured liſſe and happineſſe, mans deſirable end. <hi>The L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w of God is perfect, converting the ſoule, Pſal.</hi> 19.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The ſumme or perfection of perfection, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.96. Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found the rule of practicall righteouſneſſe, for my Text leads not to ſpeake any thing of imputative, we muſt apply mans acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereunto, that ſo from his agreement therewith, we may diſcover the righteous man, <hi>Bleſſed is the undefiled or perfect in the way that walketh in the Law of the LORD, Pſa.</hi> 119.1. this man from the manner of his converſation, God himſelfe in <hi>Job</hi> briefly deſcribes. <hi>The perfect and upright man is he who fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth GOD,</hi> and eſcheweth <hi>evill, Job</hi> 1.8. He feares, honours, loves and ſerves GOD; and ſhuns, and avoids, whatſoever comes under the notion of ſin: theſe two turn ever one upon the other, Yee <hi>that love the LORD hate evill, Pſal</hi> 97.10,
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>In odio mali dilectio boni comprobatur,</hi> Arnob. in loc.</note> the hatred of ſin is the beſt argument of our love to GOD. And no other teſtimony can we yeeld of our love to him, if we neglect to heare his commandements; and where may we better learn the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42199:7"/>love and ſervice of GOD then from his Law, for as it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſerve him we ſhould: ſo conſidering how diſinabled we are in all our faculties, it is not fit we ſhould tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon us to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>de modo,</hi> and ſtate that ſervice, leſt not knowing to doe what we ought, we diſhonoor him in our honour of him, or ſet up an Idol of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, will worſhip, which the Lord will not approve of, who as it is moſt meet, will be ſerved as himſelfe pleaſes, again, <hi>the knowledge of ſin is by the Law, Rom.</hi> 7. which in the nature of an exact rule, ſhews both what is ſtreight and what is crooked: Sin being nothing elſe
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Peccare eſt tanquam lineas tranſilire,</hi> Cic. Paradox.</note> but as it were to paſſe the line, to tranſgreſſe that rule of equity, which is the bound of all our actions. According to this Law the righteous man regulates himſelfe in an univerſall, conſtant, full and finall, obedience. 1 He loooks to all and every precept. <hi>I love all thy commandements, and all falſe wayes I utterly abhor, Pſal.</hi> 119.128. 2. He hath not heats of Religion but is conſtant in his practice: he worketh righteouſneſſe at all times. 3 He takes the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in the full latitude and extent, and looks to the letter, and to the life of the Law. 4 He continues and perſeveres in this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto his end, perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God. Which end will diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth Him not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>Which we come to ſtate the difference of the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the wicked: the maine thing the Text drives at, wherefore I paſſed the other more briefly, as taking them upon a firme ſuppoſall cleerly granted, this will diſcover the very ſoul of the deſire, and the height of the bleſſing of <hi>Balaams</hi> wiſh. The carnall eye will ſcarce diſcerne the difference, for as dyeth the wicked, ſo dyeth the righteous, as dyeth the foole, ſo the wiſe, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.15. that is the end of all, natures debt muſt be diſcharged by a diſſolution, and a generall guilt of ſin layes all under an equall forfeiture, <hi>Death paſſes upon all men in that all have ſinned, Rom.</hi> 5.12. So that death following ever upon ſn, and both of them being as generall as humane nature: we muſt finde ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall difference. Hath the righteous man a better death? but yet it is as queſtionable which is the beſt.
<note n="x" place="margin">Suet. in vit.</note> 
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> on all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42199:7"/>occaſions, when he little thought his own end to be ſo neere, even the night before he was ſlain in the Capitoll, prefers a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain death.
<note n="y" place="margin">Idemin Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtus</hi> calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good death, where the
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vbi moriendi ſenſumceleritas abſtulit.</hi> Cic. deam.</note> ſodamneſſe takes away the ſenſe of dying, and theſe two great <hi>Caeſars</hi> according to their deſires, the laſt of them not violent, yet both of them had a ſodain death: this, they ſay, he prayed againſt, that he might dye
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec morte violenta nec im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matura quod Iſraelitis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum fuerat.</hi> Grot. ex Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara.</note> neither a violent, nor a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain death, which was promiſed to the Iſraelites, to be ſure, this might be a wicked mans end: how ſodainly doe they periſh? <hi>they goe down quick into hell, Pſal.</hi> 55.15.</p>
            <p>The Moraliſt thought to dye well
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bene mori eſt libenter mori.</hi> Sen. Epiſt 61.</note> was to dye willingly, and
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Optanda mors eſt ſine metu mortis mori.</hi> Sen. Trag.</note> ſuch a death was to be wiſhed, as was without the feare of death. The good man may with <hi>Moſes</hi> on the top of <hi>Nebo,</hi> even ſee the Land of bliſſe, yet be loth to depart: the wicked may without any comfortable aſſurance of Gods favour, without any raviſhing apprehenſion of future happineſſe, and joyes after this life, be willing to leave the world: the very troubles and miſery he may here meet with, may move the man with the burthen at his back, to call for death and to embrace it,
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Anacr.</note> hoping that may put an end to all his evills, of which otherwiſe he cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how to be acquitted, for there <hi>the weary be at reſt, Iob.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Therefore they rejoyce exceedingly, and are glad when they can finde the grave, verſ.</hi> 22. when the ſorrows of death may compaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the good, and they may finde trouble and heavineſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.3.</p>
            <p n="1">1 From the pangs of death, which that expreſſe of humane feare ſpeaks in my Saviour. <hi>Father, if it be poſſible, let this cup paſſe from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 From the conſcience of their own infirmity.</p>
            <p n="3">3 From the feare of divine judgements, at which the Prophet trembled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.12. Good <hi>Agathon,</hi> death approaching, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomwhat troubled, his friends about ſaid unto him, <hi>and doſt thou father feare?</hi> to whom hee replyed,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doroth. doct.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>I have endevoured to keepe the Commandements, but I am a man, and how know I whether my workes pleaſe God: for other is the judgement of God, and other the judgement of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some may thinke it a happy death to depart in a full age, in a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42199:8"/>calme, quietly upon their beds, with their friends about them, to have a ſolemne Funerall, an honourable Interment, a ſtately Sepulcher, all theſe may a wicked man have, when the good by ſome unhappy accident may be taken off, the waters may ſwallow him up, or the beaſts devoure him, the indiſcriminating ſword of the enemy, or the noyſome peſtilence, common calamities may ſweepe him away, the fury of perſecution may uncaske his ſoule, yet this makes not the end of the one happy, or the other wretched, the Divine muſt give us ſome more reall difference.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The wicked man departs this life in the diſpleaſure of the Almighty, he laboured not to pleaſe him while here he lived, and he muſt not looke to dye in his good pleaſure, he would live without Law, and he muſt periſh by the ſentence of the Law, he may expect no mercie at his death, who contemned mercie while he lived, if he hath
<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 73.4.</note> no bands in his death, he hath no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, having no hope to reſt upon, but what an evill life can afford, which ever ends in miſery, if he be taken away in his green years, yet his ſins are ripe, if he hath filled his dayes, and lives while he be an hundred years old, he ſhall be accurſed, <hi>Iſay</hi> 65.20. <hi>He hath heaped up wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi> and God takes him away as with a <hi>whirlewinde,</hi> both living, and in his wrath, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>The wicked goe down into the inward chamber, or the cloſet of the chambers of death, Prov.</hi> 7.27. that dungeon or priſon where they are faſt locked up in miſery and iron, <hi>reſerved in everlaſting chains untill the judgement of the great day, Jude</hi> 6. the Prophet ſayes, <hi>they goe down into hell, Pſal.</hi> 55. the ſecond interpretation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is there in chiefe, their grave is hell, not onely the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward courts, but the very depth of hell, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>The grave hath dominion over them, Pſal.</hi> 49.14. They ſold themſelves ſlaves under ſin, and now death hath power over them, the firſt tranſmits them to a ſecond death, and eternall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, the worme doth not onely feaſt upon them, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> death feedeth, or banquetteth upon them, and is never ſatisfied nor they conſumed.</p>
            <p n="4">4 They have not reſt in their death,
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec mihi mors gravis eſt poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo morte do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore.</hi> Ovid. Metam. 3.</note> that which men looke upon as the end of troubles is to them but the beginning of miſery,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42199:8"/>
               <hi>the ſoule of my Lord ſhall be knit in the hundle of life, but the ſoule of my Lords enemies ſhall be in a ſling,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.19. The ſoules of the enemies of God, as in a ſling are ever reſtleſſe, their good things are at an end, their Sun is ſet, and a darke night over-ſpreds them. If hell be their grave, though there be horrid darkneſſe, and eternall night, yet no ſleepe, there they reſt not, who here ſlept, when they ſhould have watched.</p>
            <p>The death of the righteous far otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 He lies down in peace, he hath been long travelling a tedious pilgrimage, and he is now arrived at his journies end, he is come <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to his long home, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.5. and is quiet, the ſpirit returns to him that gave it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. as may be read in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſacred name, they are all quieſcent: ſo the good man, returning to him his originall, in him reſts as in his center: <hi>Marke the perfect man and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace, Pſal.</hi> 37.37. he lyeth down, and nothing can make him afraid, he is confident of the favour of God
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anima mea quid dubitas ſexaginta annis ſerviſti Chriſto &amp; mortem ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes?</hi> Hilar. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Hier.</note> as whom he hath faithfully ſerved, in a holy endeavour, keeping the Law with his whole heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.34. and where he hath fallen ſhort of his obedience, he hath returned by repentance, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to his God, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.47. and hee hopes that he whoſe paths are mercie, and truth unto ſuch as keepe his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Teſtimonies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. <hi>will ſhew mercie unto them that love him and keepe his Commandements, Exod.</hi> 20.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The death of the righteous puts an end to his ſin, he hath been in a conſtant endeavour of deading ſin in his mortall body, and now it is done, he hath gained a ſtate of innocency, in perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: then man had a power not to have ſinned, but now he ſhall have no power, or rather not ſo much weakneſſe, or imperfection that he may further ſin, a great bleſſing which onely the pious ſoul is truly apprehenſive of. Who hath obſerved the perverſneſſe of his will, and the frowardneſſe of his affections? Who hath felt the reluctancy of the fleſh againſt the ſpirit, and the motions of ſin mutining in his mortall body? Now to be tranſlated into ſuch a condition, as he cannot further diſpleaſe God, but freely and faithfully ſerve him, not being carryed away with any temptations unto ſin. Excellent is that paſſage in <hi>Nazianzen. Adam</hi> ſinning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42199:9"/>againſt God, though he were rejected Paradice, yet he doth gain thereby death, and the cutting off of ſin, leſt the evill ſhould have been immortall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Naz. Orat.</hi> 42</note> ſo the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment it ſelfe became to man a mercie, and he is well ſeconded by his comment,
<note n="r" place="margin">Nicetas.</note> after man was fallen, had he not been obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to a neceſſity of dying, he had incurred the greateſt miſery, <hi>viz.</hi> ſin working, here therefore he hath a benefit which is death, becauſe it ſtops and breakes off ſin, for although death hath the nature of a puniſhment, yet it became a mercie, not ſuffering the ſinner to be immortall, for how ſhould we without any, either feare of God or dread of judgement, have added ſin to ſin if wee had been immortall? who are ſo ſinfull to day, dying to morrow, with the immortall devill, we ſhould even have vyed offences, without either endeavour of new obedience, or remorſe by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble repentance.
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>O munde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munde ſi ſic me tenes breviter tranſeundo quid facere diu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manendo.</hi> Bern.</note> If the unclean world ſo entangle us ſo ſoon paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, what would it have done long remaining? if our vile affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſo entiſe us while we are but pilgrimes, what would they have done had we been of conſtant abode here? <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpake well,
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mihi non à diis immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vita erepta eſt ſed mors do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata eſt.</hi> Lib. 3. de Orat.</note> if he underſtood what he ſayd: <hi>Life is not taken away from me by the immortall gods, but death is given unto me,</hi> for as it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chim. Sca. Pad. Gr. 6.</note> a powerfull act of God, ſo is it likewiſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an act of grace and favour, a bleſſing rather then a curſe, as if it had been given rather for a
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non pro poena mortem dedit Deus ſed pro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medio,</hi> Ambr. de ſide reſ.</note> remedy then a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, while viper like it kils its mother ſinne, and deſtroys our deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Death puts an end to the miſeries of the righteous, thus the divine goodneſſe turns all to the beſt for them that love him, as mans puniſhment to his benefit, by ſtopping of his ſin, ſo to his greater happineſſe by ending of his miſery. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> from a paſſage in <hi>Plato</hi> or <hi>Plotinus,</hi> that father <hi>Jupiter</hi> having compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on men, made their bands ſoluble, draws this collection,
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>de Civ. Dei c.</hi> 10.</note> that the Philoſopher thought that this very thing that men are mortall in body, proceeds from the mercie of our divine Father, leſt they ſhould alwayes be held with the miſery of this life. Thus far the Text of Scripture is plain, that after <hi>Adam</hi> had taſted of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evill, whereby I am ſure he became accurſed, God thruſt him out of Paradice,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42199:9"/>and ſet a guard upon the Tree of life, leſt man ſhould taſte of that fruit and live for ever, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.22. and ſo in that he ſhortened his dayes, he ended his miſery, which there at once hath its period, from whence that cuſtome tooke its ſtirt of planting a lawrell Crown at the head of the dead mans coſſin, in token of triumph and victory obteined over the troubles and miſeries of this life, for to be ſure in the other he ſhall meet with none. Paradice would not admit of pain, much leſſe will heaven. Sorrow was part of the curſe: miſery was inconſiſtent with the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, it cannot then ſtand with eternall happineſſe. <hi>God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes, there ſhall be no more ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain, for former things are paſſed away, Rev.</hi> 21.4. the preſence of God ſhall be our joy, our delight to doe his will:
<note n="z" place="margin">Pariſ. de Rhet div.</note> our conſtant worke the praiſe of our Creator, to ſing eternall hallelujahs unto our God, and the Lambe that ſits upon the Throne.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The death of the righteous is their birth day,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Oec. in coll. 3.</note> for of a truth the Chriſtians life is hereafter, though in the ordinary phraſe of ſpeech, a man is ſayd to live while here he is, and to dye when he makes an end of dying, death being not the end of life, but the end of death, and our birth day unto eternall bliſſe, for if it be accuſtomably ſayd, a man childe is borne, when he breaks forth out of the wombe of his mother into this light, may not he be as rightly ſaid to be borne who looſed from the bonds of fleſh? is brought forth into the land of the living? it had obteined a cuſtome in the Church, that the day in which holy men departed this life, they called it the day of their nativity: and the uſuall ſolemnities they called them
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beda hom. in Ioh.</hi> 16.</note> not funeralls, but birth day feaſts, to raiſe this to a higher ſpeculation. God is the life of the ſoule, as the ſoule is of the body. While here we live our ſoule is ſeparated from its life, which is God: which St. <hi>Paul</hi> hints, <hi>While we are preſent in the world, we are abſent from the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 6. It is true, he cheriſhes us with the breathings of his ſpirit, he ſtreams the rayes of his grace into our hearts, but we enjoy not his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence, which gives fulneſſe of life and vigour into the ſoule. Again, the ſtate and condition here we are in being ſo tranſient,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42199:10"/>our life but a blaſt, but a bubble, ſuch a nothing deſerves not the title of life, but that ſtate of incorruption to which death tranſmits us, that fixed immortality that and that onely is life indeed.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Death is gaine unto the righteous. It is the end of the day, when they receive their penny, the reward of that faithfull ſervice they have yeilded unto their God,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bene moritur qui cum mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur lucrum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> Sen.</note> he dyes well, ſays the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt, who makes a gain by his death, that does the righteous man he exchanges this cottage of clay for a manſion in the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a houſe not made with hands, eternall in the heavens: he exchanges his poore poſſeſſion for a glorious inheritance: he changes this fading miſerable, for an ever bleſſed life: he
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>O preclarum diem cum ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud divinorum animorum con cilium caetum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proficiſcar &amp; cum ex hac tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba &amp; colluvio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edam,</hi> Cic. de Senect.</note> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the company and fellowſhip of ſinfull men, for the bleſſed ſociety of God, and his holy Angels, by whom he ſhall be moſt lovingly entertained.
<note n="e" place="margin">Suet. in Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtus</hi> at the Epilogue of his life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired his friends about him to give him a plaudite, as if conſcient to himſelfe that he had acted his part well upon the ſtage of this World: the righteous man ſhall have his plaudite from a better Theatre. God the Father entertains him with a <hi>well done thou good and faithfull ſervant, Mat.</hi> 25.21. God the Son entertains him with, <hi>come yee bleſſed children of my Father. Mat.</hi> 25.34. The whole hoaſt of heaven congratulate him: for if there be joy in heaven at the repentance of a ſinner, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.7. what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultation will there be at the entertainment of a righteous man into bleſſe? if they rejoyce when he is but ſet in the way, what will they doe when he comes to heaven?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Death to the righteous is his marriage day, in which he is conjoyned to his eſpouſed Lord Chriſt. Death is but the <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymphus,</hi> which preſents the faithfull ſoule unto her bridegroom. Oh happy meeting of a happy day, to be evermore happy in the imbraces of her loving and beloved Lord!
<note n="f" place="margin">Suet.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtus</hi> tooke the farewell of his life at the lips of <hi>Livia,</hi> and dyed in the comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo he left her whom he loved. The righteous man dyes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.5. at the mouth of God
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>In oſculo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</hi> Virg. in Apoc. 14.</note> at a kiſſe of Gods mouth, but it is a kiſſe of welcome, and friendly entertainment of him in whom his ſoule delighteth, as the indulgent mother takes her little one into her armes when it is about to ſleepe: So God takes his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his little righteous ones, when they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42199:10"/>ſleepe in death into the armes of his mercie, and kiſſes them with the ſweet imbraces of his love and favour, and though a while he may lay them by to reſt in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, while the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the elect ſhall be gathered together, yet his eye is ever on them, and they enjoy his preſence, <hi>in which is fulneſſe of joy.</hi> If I ſhould adde no more, is not this enough to make good, and to give us to joyne iſſue with <hi>Balaam, Let me dye the death of the righteous?</hi> but we will follow him to the ultimate period of his wiſh, <hi>and let my laſt end be like his.</hi> Though death be the end of all; yet not the laſt that betideth man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and let my afterwards,</hi> or <hi>let it be to me after death as to him.</hi> We will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then what follows death, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 9 27. <hi>after death judgement.</hi> The punctuall circumſtance of time is not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any verbe, neither <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo that whether it ſhall follow preſently, or in a longer tract, the Text leaves undetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the terme after may as well ſignifie the precedencie of things done, and order as reference to any particular time.
<note n="h" place="margin">In loc.</note> 
               <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> would ſtreighten it by altering the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that. I like not this liberty with the ſacred Text in the leaſt <hi>Iota,</hi> neither will that conclude it. For circumſtantiall notes of time, as were eaſie to evidence, are in Scripture largely, or more ſtreightly taken for yeares before or after, and it is not peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily to conclude from the Apoſtles phraſe. It may be more eaſily reſolved if we conſider man according to his eſſentiall principles: the judgement of the ſoule follows preſently upon the diſſolution, that receiveth ſentence, and <hi>is carryed by the Angels into</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams <hi>boſome,</hi> a place of reſt and happineſſe, or thruſt into torment, the body is to expect its doom, while that great day of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall judgement, theſe two being now ſeparated, we will take ſome liberty to ſpeake of ſome things, though of leſſer note, and might not ſo fully lie in <hi>Balaams</hi> wiſh, that betide the body after death. There being ſome ſmall difference obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The grave. What ever the humerous Cynicke thought,
<note n="i" place="margin">Laert. in vita Diog.</note> who cared not what became of his corps when hee was dead, yet the wiſer man ſaid, <hi>that an untimely birth was better then he that had no buriall, Eccleſ.</hi> 6.3. it was the curſe of that wicked woman, <hi>the dogs ſhall eat Jezebel by the walls of Jezreel.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42199:11"/>1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.23. <hi>and ſhe ſhall be as dung upon the face of the field,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.37. it was the doom of <hi>Jehojakim, that he ſhould have the buriall of an aſſe, Jer.</hi> 22.19. which implies that the civill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment of the body, and committing of it to earth was honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. And as the old Law was full of types and ceremonies, ſo they whoſe ſoules wereſeparated to ſeverall manſions, as if they would expreſſe this truth in a type, <hi>the faithfull were buryed by themſelves,</hi> from whence was that phraſe, <hi>to be gathered to their Fathers, Gen.</hi> 25.8. As <hi>Jacob</hi> gave commandement concerning his bones, <hi>that he would not be buryed in Egypt
<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 47.29.</note> Gather me not with the wicked,</hi> prayes the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.9. not to take notice of the ſolemnities uſed at their funerals, and to paſſe the cuſtomes from hence derived to other Nations, looke we onely to our own. They who deny the common faith, or whoſe more vileactions have been a ſcandall to their profeſſion, we eyther bury them not at all, or diſhonourably, but they who live and dye in the faith of Chriſt, and their good converſation hath given us to hope, that their bodies ſhall one day be partakers with their ſouls in bliffe, we give them a more decent buriall in places ſet a part for that uſe, the Church yard, which the Germanes call
<note n="l" place="margin">Godw. ant.</note> Gods Acre, or his field, where the bodies of his Saints are ſown corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, to ſpring and ariſe again incorruptible and immortall.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The reſurrection though our bodies doe moulder, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve into, yet they doe not loſe themſelves in the duſt, they onely leave their weakneſſe and corruption which adheares unto them by the contagion of ſin, from which being purged, the ſubſtance of the body returns again: to prove that there is a reſurrection were too large a digreſſion, and a needleſſe labour, it being ſo cleere a conſtat among Chriſtians, that we hold it an article of our faith. We are baptized not onely for the remiſſion of ſins, but alſo into the reſurrection of the fleſh, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. from whence I conceive the Greeks call baptiſme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or putting on of immortality, and again, we lay down out bodies in the duſt, in the ſure and certain hope thereof. It was an ill reading of that Text, <hi>the wicked ſhall not ariſe in judgement, Pſal.</hi> 1.5. which ſtrained that gloſſe
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cyr. Hier. cat. 18. &amp; Theoph. in Joh. 3.</note> not to judgement but to condemnation, the true reading is, <hi>they ſholl not ſtand in judgement,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42199:11"/>according to the
<note n="*" place="margin">Stare in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio.</note> Latine phraſe, <hi>they ſhall not be acquitted, but fall when they are judged.</hi> For as <hi>Aquinas</hi> rightly argues
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Suppl.</hi> 3. <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis qu.</hi> 75. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> that which is taken from the nature of the ſpecies, is alike found in every individuall of the ſame ſpecies: the reſurrection is ſuch, and therefore it belongs to every particular. Every one muſt ariſe, the moſt wretched liver and the falſe beleever, but here is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſurrectio &amp; incredulis parata eſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria autem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la credentibus repromiſſa eſt:</hi> Euſ. Em. hom. 1. de Symb.</note> though all ariſe, yet the glory of the reſurrection is onely promiſed unto the faithfull. Which was that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſo earneſtly endevoured after,<hi>if I may by any meanes obteine the reſurrection of the dead, Phil.</hi> 3.11. that of the wicked not deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the title, being but an upſtanding to everlaſting death. Here the body being rayſed by the power of GOD out of the duſt, meets it ſoul again, and are conjoyned together, to the righteous a joyfull meeting, one of them being happy in the other, and both of them in a full expectation of a never ending felicity. Sad to the wicked ſoul, being fettered again to the body, like malefactors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſories in the ſame guilt, to receive together a juſt, but fearfull recompence of reward.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Judgement is an act of juſtice terminated upon man. A ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence given by GOD upon his actions. There is a twofold judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſigned by Divines; a Seſſion, and a grand Aſſize; a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and a generall. For every man is to be conſidered as he is a ſingular perſon, in himſelf, and as his ſins have had influence into others. And as he is a member of mankind.</p>
            <p n="1">1 As he is an individuall, and particular perſon, ſo is he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by God preſently after his death, when he is doomed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what he hath done in the body, although not fully, becauſe not in the body, but onely in the ſoule, that onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, and having its ſentence, the body lying aſleepe in its duſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As he is a part of mankind, ſo he is called at the great and generall day, when there ſhall be a full ſummons, and an univerſall appearance of all the living that ever were, and as generall a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, neither yet does God judge twice for the ſame thing, and inflict double puniſhment for one ſin, but that which before was not compleatly inflicted, then ſhall the wicked be given up to be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42199:12"/>tormented, and the good glorified in ſoule and body both, and thereſeems to be in this equity, that the body which hath been a fellow worker with the ſoul, either of holineſſe unto life, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe unto death, ſhould have her part proportionable in the reward, by which generall judgement the righteouſneſſe of God ſhall be acquitted and vindicated from all ſlander not onely from the teſtimony of every guilty conſcience, but alſo by the cleere acknowledgement of every one ſummoned to appeare at the barre: <hi>Righteous O God art thou, and juſt are thy judgements.</hi> The ſecrets of all hearts being then revealed, and the full num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of each mans ſins being then made up, for wicked men finiſh not their ſins with their dayes, <hi>ſome mens ſins following after judgement,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24. they give while they live bad examples, which are drawn into practice, they leave behinde them the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of unrighteous deeds which multiply to poſterity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them their firſt and proper parent. So the vertuous lives of good men lead others by the hand unto holineſſe, and their faith is filed for poſterity. <hi>Abraham</hi> is long ſince in bliſſe, yet is his faith impreſſed in the hearts of his children who walke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>In the ſteps of the faith of that holy Father, Rom.</hi> 4.12. how will it adde to the crown of rejoycing as glory, of that bleſſed Saint to ſee ſo many trails after him in that tread of faith and righteouſneſſe which he hath before trodden out? how will it bliſſe thoſe faithfull diſpenſers of the word, and other holy men, who by their devout faith and religious practice, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted many unto righteouſneſſe, to appeare with thoſe they have brought to fight under Chriſt his banner? might I rather in the rerelead up but one convert, then to march in the van of all the worlds happineſſe, or triumphant glory. The Son of man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mounted on the throne of his Majeſty, then follows diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of actions. <hi>Heavens records ſhall be brought forth, the books ſhall be opened, the book of life, and according to their works writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in that book, the dead ſhall be judged. Apoc.</hi> 20.12. Not to enter into any nice School diſputes concerning this book what it is, how mens actions are therein regiſtred, and enrolled: when the Holy Spirit is pleaſed to beſilent, I will not over-ſawcily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42199:12"/>It is enough our actions are all therein recorded: not a good work, word, almſ-deed, prayer, but it is there noted: not a tear of contrition for ſin that fals to the ground, but GOD lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches it: <hi>Put thou my teares in thy bottle, are not theſe things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in thy book? Pſal.</hi> 66.8. As on the other ſide not a wicked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, idle word, vile thought, but they are there recorded like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <hi>Theſe things thou haſt done and I kept ſilence, and thou thoughteſt I had been ſuch an one as thy ſelf, but I will reprove thee, and ſet them inorder before thine eyes, Pſal.</hi> 50.21. He now unſeen, ſees, and obſerves what afterwards openly he will produce: when he ſhall ſit in righteouſneſſe to judge the world. When hee ſhall come to try our actions, and accordingly ſever the good and bad with his diſcriminating fan in his hand: parting the chaffe and ſoyle from the cleaner grains: where the good wheat ſhall be layd up in Gods granery: and the evill like the tares caſt into the fire. Having thus ſpoken of what betides man after death I now come to cloſe with the ordinary reading, and diſcover unto you the ultimate period, the laſt end of the righteous man. The LORD hath taken him unto himſelfe to be with him eternally bleſſed, bleſſed to eternity, but the difficulty will be to deſcribe unto you what bleſſedneſſe is,
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Futura bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo acquiri poteſt aeſtimari non poteſt,</hi> Euſ. Em.</note> though here wee muſt labour, and lay earneſt for it, yet we cannot rightly eſteem of it, to ſay it is
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt ſtatus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnium bonorum congregatione perfectus.</hi> Boet. de conſ. Phil. 3. lib. 3. proſ. 2.</note> a perfectſtate conſiſting in the aggregation, and collection of all good things. While we take it thus up in the groſſe, it leſſe affects us. And to take it up in particulars, thinking thereby more fully to explain it, wee ſhall fall as ſhort. When as Saint <hi>Paul, who was rapt up into the third heaven,</hi> ſits down in an extaſie, <hi>ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eye hath ſeen, neyther eare hath heard, neyther hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive the good things that GOD hath layd up for them that love him:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. It were I think impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent temerity in any one to go about to determine. None I am ſure did ever yet by a <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder ſcale Heaven, and make fuller diſcovery of that land of the living; that hee might make us a more perfect relation.
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>App. ad Aug. tom.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>The kingdom of GOD is greater then all report, it is better then it can be prayſed, it ſurpaſſes all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it is more excellent then all glory that can be imagined: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42199:13"/>ought I therefore to be ſilent in what I can ſay, becauſe I cannot what I would, neyther becauſe we ſay GOD is ineffable, therefore may we not ſpeak of him what we are able, ſo that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve more then we ſpeake.</hi>] And ever bound our words with fear, and piety. <hi>What we cannot conceive GOD hath revealed unto us by his Spirit.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. But it is obſervable, where the Spirit hath revealed unto us theſe unconceivable things, condeſcending to our underſtanding, to move us it hath ſet them forth under the notion of temporall goods, which wee make great account of. Which yet in our conceits thereof if we reſt, we are as far beneath them, as earth is heaven. The Spirit ſayth the righteous ſhall have a Kingdom, and weare upon their heads a crown of righteouſnes, they ſhall be clothed with long white robes of innocence, they ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> at his table in that Kingdom: which ſhall be richly furniſhed; to do the will of GOD,
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Delectatio erit cibus, Pariſ.</note> and our delight in him ſhall be our meat: and he ſhall give us to drink of the rivers of his pleaſure. This kingdom ſhall be theirs by a ſure inheritance, being coheirs with Chriſt the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Son of GOD. They ſhall enter into their maſters joy, where they ſhall bear a part in that heavenly quire, to ſing perpetuall hallelujahs unto the Lambe that ſitteth upon the throne. Heaven ſhall be theirs, a treaſury of riches, and all wealth: and to adde to the perfection of theſe, of that kingdom there ſhall be no end. The crown of glory ſhall bee immarceſſible, it ſhall not breed like <hi>Jonahs</hi> gourd, a worm to eat it; our garment of immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty no moth ſhall fret it: thoſe riches no canker ſhall deſtroy them; thoſe joys ſhall have no alloy of grief to abate them. Thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights ſhall breed no ſurfet. Thoſe ſtreams of pleaſures ſhall not run dry, but be mayntained by a continuall ſpring: that day ſhall know no night, the Sun ſhall not be ecclipſed, nor clouded by darkneſſe, for the Lambe is the light of the new <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that eternall city affords all things eternall; and they ſhall be for ever to enjoy them. The righteous ſhall enter into everlaſting life.
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 74.</note> becauſe men love to live here on earth, life is promiſed them; and becauſe they are affraid to dye, therefore eternall life is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them. What doeſt thou love to live? thou ſhalt have it.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42199:13"/>What doſt thou feare to dye? thou ſhalt not ſuffer it. ô living life, and everlaſtingly bleſſed! where is reſt, without labour; wealth without loſſe: health, without languiſhing: abundance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out want: perpetuity, without corruption, life, without death: where is light, without darkneſſe: knowledge without ignorance: underſtanding, without errour: reaſon, without obſcurity: me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, without forgetfulneſſe: where what ever is deſirable is to be enjoyed, and nothing ſhall be deſired that is not meet. Where GOD ſhall be ſeen without end, loved beyond meaſure, prayſed without weariſomneſſe, who in that he is the perfection of being, ſhall ſatisfie the underſtanding; perfection of goodneſſe, ſhall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the will: and truly amiable, ſhall fill our affections. Wee ſhall be amazed at his juſtice, admire his mercy, be raviſhed with his goodneſſe. What ſhall I adde more? The righteous ſhall ſit at the right hand of Chriſt, they ſhall not onely enjoy GODS preſence, but ſhall be ever happy in a gracious union, and conſtant communion with the Godhead.
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>De conſ. Phi. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>proſ.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Boetius</hi> rayſes a high pitch: becauſe by the gaining of bleſſedneſſe men are made bleſſed, and bleſſedneſſe is the divinity it ſelf, it is manifeſt men are bleſſed by obteining the divinity: and as by obteining of juſtice, men are made juſt: and by obteining of wiſdom, men are wiſe: ſo (ſays he) by obteining the divinity men are made gods: every bleſſed man therefore is a GOD, who though but one by nature, it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not but that there may be many by participation. GOD pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes himſelfe indeed to <hi>Abraham an exceeding great reward, Gen.</hi> 15.1. of which the Prophet <hi>David</hi> lays hold, <hi>the LORD is the portion of mine inheritance, Pſal.</hi> 16.5. heare Saint <hi>John, We are now the ſons of GOD, but it doth not yet appear what wee ſhall be: but wee know when hee ſhall appeare, wee ſhall be like him: for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. The ſight of GOD which is the promiſe of a righteous man, makes him like even unto GOD. I can rayſe my meditations no higher, I muſt here reſt: adde, onely if I may rayſe your affections more to deſire the righteous mans end, by ſhewing you on the contrary, the fearfull, and miſerable end of the wicked man.</p>
            <p n="1">1 As he dyes in GODS diſpleaſure, ſo is he deprived of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42199:14"/>glorious prefence for ever. The greatneſſe of this puniſhment is not to be valued, in that ſo great an evill is the privation of any good to be eſteemed, as is that good which it deprives us of: when as therefore the good of which the damned are deprived is infinite, ſo muſt the puniſhment be: to be caſt out of GODS preſence, to be under his eternall enmity, ten thouſand hels is not ſuch an evill; as to have omnipotency an irreconciled enemy, and he who is all Goodneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Hee is given over to the tyranny of the Devill: and juſt that who while he lived here was ſubject, ſerved, and obeyed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, when hee dyes ſhould be enſlaved to, and poſſeſſed of him. And with whom by a diſobedient will hee would partake in ſin, hee ſhould though unwilling, partake with him in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be tormented of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Torture in hell fire, which burns, and yet conſumes not, but the wicked are repaired to everlaſting flames: as the Poetsfabled of <hi>Premetheus,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Heſiod. Theog.</note> whoſe liver the devouring Eagle eat in the day, and what was then devoured grew again in the night: ſo in the midſt of thoſe conſuming flames,
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Damnata na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura dat pabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; accepit incrementum.</hi> Euſeb. Em. ho. 1. ad Mon.</note> the damned nature yields fuell, and receives increaſe. If the finger in the flame (yea, but a little time) is not now to be endured; how unſufferable will it be, body and ſoul to be ſcorched in hell flames eternally?</p>
            <p n="4">4 The puniſhment in all his ſenſes: not onely his feeling with ſmart, but his ſight ſhall be grieved with moſt horrid apparitions, his hearing terrified with bitter out-cryes, and gnaſhing of teeth, his ſmelling offended with intollerable ſtench, his taſte tormented with hunger and thirſt, and infeſted with a more bitter humour then gall or wormwood.</p>
            <p n="5">5 A collection of griefs, and all miſeries ſhall flow in upon him: <hi>I will heap miſchiefs upon them, I will ſpend mine arrows upon them, Deut.</hi> 32.23. not one, or a ſecond, or ſome few, but a heap of miſchiefs ſhall fall upon the wicked: and GOD ſetting him up as a butt, will even empty the quiver of the arrows of his fury upon them. Greatneſſe of grief may now take away the ſenſe of grief, but then it ſhall ſharpen them.</p>
            <p n="6">6 A worm never dying, a conſcience of ſin: now ſins are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42199:14"/>veyled under the huke of delight, and appear not ſo foule, then ſhall they appear in their filthineſſe, to the grief of the guilty: in the ſight of which they ſhall diſpleaſe themſelves, and repent without any profit.</p>
            <q>LORD, what contrarieties ſeem to accord in the puniſhment of the wicked to make them wretched? they ſee thee and they ſee thee not: they ſee thy frown, and not thy face. They are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of life, yet they live: they are dead, yet they endure, and are ſenſible of miſery. The fire burns them yet conſumes them not: it flames, yet gives no light. A horrid darkneſſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreads them, yet there is a cleer medium to ſee themſelves mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable but can ſee nothing whereby they may be happy.</q>
            <p n="7">7 And that which makes him fully miſerable to ſuffer all theſe eternally, the greateſt puniſhment if it may have a period may better be endured, but ſo great, and endleſſe is the ſum of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. It may well be noted for injuſtice, and tyranny in <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who would not be reconciled to the offender: and loved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve men to torment. So that a guilty man dying ere hee came to the rack, he cryes out, <hi>Carnulius</hi> hath eſcaped: and paſſing by the priſon, one entreating of him to haſten his puniſhment, hee made this reply,
<note n="z" place="margin">Suet. in Tib.</note> 
               <hi>Nondum tecum in gratiam redii.</hi> I am not yet returned into favour with thee. GOD is no <hi>Tiberius,</hi> no ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, yet will not be reconciled to the guilty ſoule, the reaſon is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. For ſin being an offence againſt an infinite goodneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves an infinite puniſhment, which man being not able to endure, muſt ſuffer eternally. And again, the ſinner dying unrepenting ſins eternally, and then it is juſt that if man ſins, GOD ſhould puniſh unto eternity. Who is it now that ſhall deeply conſider the bleſſed departure and happy end of the righteous: and on the other ſide the deſperate death, and unhappy end of the wicked, but will conclude, that there was good cauſe which did move <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> thus to wiſh? and who is not ready to joyn in requeſt with him, <hi>that his laſt end may be like the righteous man:</hi> What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſhall be to ſhew you, how <hi>our laſt end maybe like his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Live the life of the righteous,</hi> Reſt not in a bare wiſh as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, good deſires are like good dreams, which vaniſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42199:15"/>when we awake, and come to nothing: and doe but deceive him that truſts in them, the worſt of men may wiſh ſo well unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but I dare not promiſe them they ſhall ſo obtein it. All would have the Crown, but they will not try the combat: they would have the penny, but they would not ſweat in the vineyard: they would wiſh the righteous mans death, but they will not live the life of the righteous.
<note n="a" place="margin">Cor. à Lap.</note> For to dye well is happineſſe, to live well is labour: but one is not granted without the other. Eternity depends upon death: that upon a good or bad life, once to periſh is to periſh eternally.
<note n="b" place="margin">Plut. in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</note> 
               <hi>Iphicrates</hi> ſayd it was a ſpeech unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of an Emperour to ſay, <hi>I had not thought,</hi> how much more unworthy of a Chriſtian is it to ſay, I had not thought there had been ſuch difference between a holy and an unholy life. I had not thought that Eternity had depended upon this momentany being. To all the advertiſements thou haſt had before, take this at laſt, which I ſhall again repeat: Upon a holy life depends a good death, and upon that Eternity, and if thou periſheſt once, thou periſheſt eternally.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ. Em. ho.</hi> 7. <hi>de Paſſ.</hi>
               </note> It is in the power of this preſent life that that may be happy which is everlaſting; for if thou leadeſt this preſent well, the future cannot be miſerable: if thou feareſt to die evill, feare to live evill, but feare not, he cannot die evill who liveth well. Now as that is a good and wel-led life, which is paſſed in holineſſe, and vertuous actions, that an evill one which is led in wickedneſſe; anſwerably the death is to be weighed from the forepaſſed actions of life, ſo that if the life be led in a religious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of God his Law, in a holy obedience to his will, the death cannot be bad: for it is a tranſlation to immortality. But if otherwiſe, it is neceſſary it muſt be evill, for it tranſmits to eternall miſery: how comfortably could a good old <hi>Simeon</hi> pray that hymne, and ſing while he prayed, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace:</hi> with what a religious confidence could old <hi>Hilarin</hi> farewell with his ſoule
<note n="d" place="margin">Hier. de Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</note> who had ſerved his God ſixty years? the conſcience of that faithfull ſervice, ſatisfied, that his future being could not bee unhappy. A heavenly life here on earth, muſt needs give ſecurity of a happy life in heaven, he that lives here, hath no cauſe to feare to die here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42199:15"/>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Doroth. doctr. 8.</note> for indeed I call the holy, the onely life: the wicked man hath a being here, but onely the righteous man lives. We uſe to count our dayes, and number our years according to the time we are on earth. Deceive not thy ſelf who ever thou art: Compute thou haſt only lived that day in which thou haſt denyed thine own will, in which thou haſt reſiſted thy corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in the which thou haſt not tranſgreſſed the rule of equity. Compute thou haſt onely lived that day which malice, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, envy, or pride hath not clouded, which hath not been waſted in ſin, in which thou haſt ſtood upon thy guard, and haſt not been foyled by fleſhly temptations. Compute thou haſt only lived that day, which pious meditation and holy practice hath enlightned; not which the darkneſſe of ſin hath turned into a night, apply only unto thy life, that day the benefit of which by a holy converſation hath redounded unto thy ſoul. The reſt is but idle paſtime, a phraſe which humours moſt men well, but ſuch empty cyphers will prove nothing but reall woes, at heavens account. Shall we compute that a day of life in which men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume eternity, and heape unto themſelves puniſhments never to have an end, ſuch a life tends unto, and ends in death, and is in truth but a death, live therefore while here thou art, ſow the ſeeds of holineſſe, that thou mayſt reape happineſſe. Bud forth in the bloſſomes of a future life, that thou mayſt gather the fruit, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: the preſent muſt anſwer to the future, the worldly luſts ſubdue thy corrupt appetites, let the ſpirit of God rule in thy heart, ſet thy affections on things above, let thy converſation be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and hope well, one day thou mayſt come thither, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hercules,</hi> he had never been inrolled among the gods in heaven, if he had not laid out his way thither while he lived: ſo if we walke not in that holy way while here we live, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be regiſtred with the Saints in bliſſe.
<note n="f" place="margin">Beru.</note> There is no way unto the Kingdom, without the firſt-fruits of the Kingdome, neither may they hope to reign there as Kings, who have not here ruled over their properluſts. If yee looke God ſhould take you as he did <hi>Enoch,</hi> you muſt as he walke with God: a holy, ever uſhers in a happy life. It was a bold and ſharpe reply of thoſe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42199:16"/>to <hi>Alexander,</hi> an exemplary Prince for Armes and Arts, who paſſing ſome territories where his conquering ſword had made him maſter, hearing of learned men (as his manner was) ſent for them, and propounded to them many queſtions, they gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him good reſolution, as an argument of his royall ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he would have them aske him what they pleaſed, that hee might grant it to them: they joyntly asked of him immortality: the Prince began to ſmile, before, ſayes he, I thought you wiſe men, but now I thinke you fools, to aske of me immortality, who my ſelfe am mortall. While I conſider the condition and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the moſt of men, I may make the like demand, give me immortality: if nature prompts them, or Religion hath better taught them that they are mortall: I make my reply with them to <hi>Alexander,</hi> why then doe you live evill, letting looſe the reynes of all kinde of ſin and wickedneſſe, as if you were immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall? as if you had no thought of death or feare of judgement. For if we weigh well the actions of the moſt, can we judge any otherwiſe of them? for where is he who lives according to the decorum of heaven? whoſe practice anſwers to that holy faith, he would be accounted to make profeſſion of? Philoſophy tels us that naturally men deſire the chiefeſt good, eternalll happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But all this while Religion hath been preached in the world, it cannot worke ſo much upon mens affections, as to win them to the right means of gaining of it, they would obtein the chiefe good, yet they would not be good.
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 12. <hi>ae verb. Dom.</hi>
               </note> Doeſt thou not ſee how thou oughteſt to bluſh at thy ſelfe, who wouldeſt have all things good, yet thy ſelfe wouldeſt not be good? thy houſe thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have filled with goods, and ſhall it have thee an evill maſter? What is it that thou wouldeſt have ill, not a wife, not a childe, not a ſervant, not a houſe, not a garment, not thy ſhoos, and yet thou careſt not though thy ſelfe be evill: thinke better of thy life then of thy ſhoos. All things about thee, if they be elegant and faire pleaſe, and wilt thou be vile and filthy in thy ſelfe? if thy good things could ſpeake unto thee which thou enjoyeſt, would they not ſay unto thee, as thou wouldeſt have us good, ſo doe we deſire thee to be, and may they not ſecretly murmur to God
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42199:16"/>againſt thee? behold, thou haſt given ſo many good things to this man, yet he himſelfe is evill. Cannot he who gave theſe good things, and makes them good unto thee, if thou diſpleaſe him take away the comfortable enjoyment of them, turne the bleſſing into a curſe, thy proſperity into thy deſtruction? get therefore with them his good will, by doing his good will, that at laſt he may give thee better, and more reall, the true goods. Conjoyne thy ſelfe to the fellowſhip of Saints, be of the holy Church here below, that thou maiſt be one of the Church triumphant in glory. Labour according to the grace of God given unto thee to doe the will of God here on earth, as they doe in heaven, that ſo thou maiſt doe it more perfectly hereafter with them.
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum quibus fuerit vobis conſortium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votionis erit &amp; communio dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis,</hi> Leo Ser. 5. de Epip.</note> For with whom we have a conſort devotion, we ſhall have a community of dignity. If thou wouldeſt have the righteous mans end, live as doe the righteous: let it be thy delight to doe the will of God, order thy actions according to that perfect rule he hath given thee: walke in an univerſall obedience to all the Laws. There is, ſays the Moraliſt, a concatenation of vertues, and it is not one but all that entitles the vertuous man. The Jews ſay that God ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered all the Commandements in one breath, I am ſure they are linked together. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill Neither ſhalt thou commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Neither ſhalt thou ſteale, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 5.17, 18. the breach of one diſſolves the chaine. An offence is not in this or that onely, but in any, and <hi>he that offends in one is guilty of all, Jam.</hi> 2.10. in that he offends againſt juſtice, and the will of the Law-giver, who gave the one and gave the other, and is equally diſobeyed in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He that obſerves one commandement, not another, he does his own will, not Gods, and did his corrupt affections equally prompt him, he would diſobey in what he doth obſerve. Looke not onely to the affirmative precepts, but alſo to the negative, knowing the latter may be as deſtructive as the former,
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Peccat ille qui imperata neglexerit, ſed plus peccat qui interdicta non ſervat</hi> Hier. p. 3. Ep. 2.</note> if not more: looke not onely to the greater, but alſo to the leſſer, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there is an obligation upon thee from God to both. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19. He that ſhall unbinde or unlooſe <hi>one of theſe leaſt Commandements,</hi> one, and of the leaſt he ſhall be called
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Minimus nullus,</hi> Gloſſ. Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>the leaſt in the Kingdom of God.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Contemptus cujuſcunque praecepti praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientis iniuria eſt.</hi> Hier. par. 3. Ep. 18.</note> the contempt of any
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42199:17"/>command is the injury of him that does command, and therefore the holy Prophet, <hi>I love all thy commandements, and all falſe wayes I utterly abhor, Pſal.</hi> 119.128.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Do righteouſneſſe at all times, Pſal.</hi> 106.3. Have not heats of Religion, but ever regulate thy actions, by the rule of truth, with a perpetuall conſtancy; the ſchool obſerves well, that affirmative precepts binde always, but not at all times: negative always and at all times, and it may be obſerved, all the morall precepts of God, (the fourth of the firſt Table, and the firſt of the ſecond excepted) for which there is good cauſe, in that imperious inſolent ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors may counter command the eternall, run in the negative, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us to a continuall performance. Let opportunity beare no plea, nor privacie give thee no advantage to commit iniquity: in that the eye of juſtice ever watches over thee, though the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of corrupter times would connive at ſome faults, yet ken that Text in the righter reading <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Serve the Lord,</hi> not the time, though the multitnde of tranſgreſſors might ſeeme to beare thee out: yet know,
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vbi maior eſt peccantium turba, maior eſt divinitatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuria.</hi> Salv. de gub. li. 3.</note> the greater number of offenders the more God is offended, and take not licence for the leaſt offence, knowing the Law being of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall truth, is not variable by circumſtances of time, place, or looſer practice, but tyes to a conſtant and perpetuall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Walke in the full latitude of every commandement.</hi> Looke to every branch, every Iota, and point thereof, reſt not in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but minde likewiſe the more inward and ſpirituall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: abſtain not onely from the outward act, but keepe cloſe ſentinell upon the heart, which if thou canſt not keepe free from injected thoughts, yet delight not thy ſelfe in them, leſt they win conſent, but ſmother them there, ſo ſoon as they be diſcovered, the Cockatrice is with more eaſe and leſſe danger, cruſhed in the egg ere it be diſcloſed. My Saviour will not acquit him from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, who hath abſtained from the forbidden bed, but tels us the luſtfull looke carries a guilt with, and is adultry in the heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. man is not innocent, when the act does not perfect the will, when hee brings not forth the evill which the heart
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42199:17"/>conceives,
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concupiſcere nefas eſt, quod fieri crimen eſt,</hi> Hier. par. 3. Ep. 15.</note> when it is an iniquity to think what it is a ſin to do.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Continue in this obedience unto thy lives end. <hi>Faint not, nor be we ary of well doing: Finiſh thy courſe, be faithfull unto the death for the crown of life, Revel.</hi> 2.10.
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non inchoaſſe ſed perſeciſſe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlitia eſt,</hi> Idem Ep. 22.</note> It is not to begin well, but to perſevere in what is well begun, that is perfect juſtice. Nay, I may ſay,
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>In caſſum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num agitur ſi ante vitae ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minnm deſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quia fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra velociter currit, qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſquam ad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam venerit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicit.</hi> Greg. Mor.</note> it is in vain to begin if wee perſiſt not, as to run in the race if we hold not unto the mark. Evill beginnings may be corrected by a following practice, but an evill end tranſmits us to remedileſſe eternall miſery. If the Word of GOD may carry it, divine Truth ſpeaks thus much. <hi>The righteouſneſſe of the righteous ſhall not deliver him in the day of his tranſgreſſion, as for the wickedneſſe of the wicked, hee ſhall not fall thereby in the day that hee turneth from his wickedneſſe: neyther ſhall the righteous be able to live in the day that hee ſinneth, Ezek.</hi> 33.12. the like is to be read, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22, 24. Ill beginnings do not prejudice the true convert, the benefit of good beginnings are forfeited through future failings. If we at laſt forſake GOD, and liſt our ſelves in the Devils ſervice, it may be juſt with him there to leave us under his power,
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jon. Ep. ad Magn.</note> whoſe we are, while to him we yield our ſelves, to have our reward from and with him. It is not enough to be, and live, but we muſt likewiſe dye Saints, if we expect to be, and live ſuch for ever. It is the end crowns the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, perſeverance confirms the righteous man. Thus the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man orders himſelf though hee reſts not in his own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which is of the Law; <hi>but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſnes which is of GOD by faith, Phil.</hi> 3.9. So
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>De ſanctis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus annotan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt ita ſub vet. Teſt. vixiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ut uon illinc reſtiterunt, ſed aſpirarunt ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ad novum adeoque certam cius communionem amplexi ſunt.</hi> Calvin. Inſtit. lib. 2. c. 11. Sect. 10.</note> the holy Patriarchs which lived under the old Teſtamentreſted not there, but ever aſpired unto the grace of the Goſpel, and ſo embraced its certain communion.
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnis anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas colentium verum DEVM omnis numerus apud ſecula priora ſanctorum, ſacra fide vixit &amp; placuit, &amp; neque Patriarchis, neque Prophetis, neque quiſquam omnino ſanctorum, niſi in redemptione Domini noſtri</hi> Jeſu Chriſti <hi>ſalus &amp; iuſtificatiofuit,</hi> Leo Serm. 1. de Paſſ.</note> Faith hath been the ſure means of ſalvation to ſo many as have obteined it. <hi>The promiſe of faith, the law which was after given could not diſanull. Gal.</hi> 3.17. The object of faith though not ſo cleerly exhibited, untill theſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42199:18"/>latter ages of the World, yet faith in the promiſe did bear date, and that of grace was (after the fall) the firſt, if not the onely cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: without queſtion the onely poſſible means of obteining ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification before God. Order therefore thy life as if there were no Goſpel, but dye as if there were no Law, live as if there were not anothers righteouſntſſe to plead for thee, but dye in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of thy Saviours merit. Walk towards Heaven in that
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nihil crit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodi, ſivitae ſanctitatem, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimemus eſſe viam, non qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem quae adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aperiat in gloriam coeleſtis regni, ſed qua clecti à Deo ſuo in eius m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtationem du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur: quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do haec bona eius voluntas eſt, glorificari quos ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> Calvin. In ſtit. l. 3. c 18. Sect. 4.</note> perfect way, a ſtrict obedience to GODS Law, but let faith open for thee the gate to bleſſedneſſe, let ſuch be thy life, that ſuch may be thy laſt end.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Dye the death of the righteous.</hi> There is 1 a death for ſin, 2 a death in ſin, 3 a death to ſin. A death for ſin, that is, that we all ſuffer a juſt puniſhment for our offences.
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. c</hi> 88.</note> It was a branch of the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereſie, that <hi>Adam</hi> though hee had not ſinned, yet he ſhould have dyed; not by the merit of ſin, but by a neceſſity of nature. Such a principle might better be allowed in a
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mors naturae finis eſt non poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> Sen. ſual. 7.</note> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt then a Chriſtian. For though <hi>Adam</hi> were a mortall
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ideo factum eſt per peccatum non mortale quoderat, ſed mortuum quod non ſicret niſi peccaret.</hi> Lomb. Sent. li. 2. diſt. 19.</note> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet had hee kept his innocency, by grace hee had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from death. <hi>For the body is dead, becauſe of ſin, Rom.</hi> 8.10. and ſo my Saviour while hee would ſtand in our ſtead to anſwer for us, <hi>he dyed for the ungodly. Rom,</hi> 5.10,</p>
            <p n="2">2 A death in ſin, ſo we dye yea, daily dye and will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it. The drunkard that drinks down iniquity, &amp; ſwils himſelf into the condition of a beaſt: <hi>thinks not that there is death in the pot</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. The luſtfull Wanton that awayts the twylight, and then ſlips to his carrion, <hi>conſiders not that the harlots houſe is the way to hell, going down to the chambers of death, Proverbs</hi> 7 27. The doubling tongue that dallies with the heart, feels not when it kils its own ſoul. Thus too many Felons play with their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A death to ſin, this is the Saints death: who mortifie their members on earth, and kill ſin in their mortall bodies. <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cious in the ſight of the LORD is the death of his Saints. Pſal.</hi> 16.15.
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vbi homo occiditur mundo non ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatione ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuum ſed fine vitiorum.</hi> Leo Ser. in nat. Machab.</note> When men <hi>dye</hi> unto the World, not by an end of being but by an end of ſinning: forſaking thoſe former accuſtomed ways of wickedneſſe, and living in godlineſſe, which before they did not, which is a kind of death and reſurrection in us. <hi>Bleſſed,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42199:18"/>and holy is he who hath his part in the firſt reſurrection, of ſuch the ſecond death ſhall have no power. Apoc.</hi> 20.6. If the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that bleſſed life which follows upon the death to ſin may nothing affect us: wee might rayſe (I think) arguments from the other members of the diviſion to move us. Death in ſin is the ſoul of death,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Naz. Orat. 19.</note> the death of the ſoul: it divides GOD from the ſoul who is the life thereof. How circumſpect, if wee obſerve it, are men to preſerve bodily life, and the life of life how do they neglect. Wee will avoid the infected houſe, <hi>and the
<note n="b" place="margin">1 King. 8.38.</note> plague of our heart</hi> wee cheriſh in our boſome. If our body be wounded wee run to the Chyrurgeon, and we wound our ſouls by our ſins which cut deeper then any two edged ſword, killing that which is immortall, and yet we are ſenſleſſe of the miſery. If nature, or art could help us, we would preſerve our bodies everlaſting: and our ſouls ſhall we voluntarily murther? Oh! what pity is it to ſee how men trifle away life, ſoul, ſalvation, and imbezle eternall bliſſe for a thing of nought. They dote upon and humour every vile affection, though to their endleſſe deſtruction. <hi>Man drinketh iniquity like water, Job</hi> 15.16. like hungry Rats that raven down their own bane wee thirſt, wee drink, wee dye. Again, for ſin wee dye, that it is which hath cauſed all thoſe ſorrows, and vexations, troubles, and infirmities; hath brought all that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of evils that hath broken in upon mankinde. That it is which hath ſeparated the ſoul from the body and layed in its duſt.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Peccatum mortis pabulum</hi> Lact. li. 4.</note> Sin is that whereby death lives, and wee dye: it procured the death of the Son of God. Hee dyed for our ſins, that wee ſhould dye unto ſin, <hi>that as Chriſt was rayſed from the dead by the glory of the Father: ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſſe of life. Rom.</hi> 6.4. Oh, let not that precious bloud of the Son of GOD be ſpilt in vain! <hi>he gave himſelf for us, that hee might redeem us from all iniquity, Titus</hi> 2.14. and he reedeemed us by ſuch a price that hee may worthily poſſeſſe us. I cannot read that paſſage in
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. <hi>de elem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> without a moved paſſion, nor take it into deeper meditation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a melting heart, where hee brings in the Devill at the day of judgement, as it were, inſulting over my ever bleſſed Saviour. I (ſays he) for thoſe whor thou ſeeſt with me, have neyther been buffeted, nor ſcourged, nor born the croſſe, nor ſhed my bloud, nor
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42199:19"/>redeemed them by the price of my paſſion; neyther do I promiſe unto them an heavenly Kingdom; neyther do I recall them to Paradiſe reſtoring immortality: yet what precious and great gifts, gotten in a long time, and by large expence, by pawning, and imbezelling their goods; even while they are ſcorned and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at, and ſomtime by a popular fury even ready to be ſtoned: ſhew mee the like preſident in the pale of thy Church, thoſe rich men flowing with abundance, are they ſo free towards thee? will they give ſo much to thee? though they might thereby tranſlate their poſſeſſions into everlaſting treaſures. Yet in theſe expences for me none are fed, none are clothed, none are comforted, but all things are prodigally and fooliſhly waſted. In thy poor, thou art clothed: in thy hungry thou art fed, thou doſt promiſe eternal life to them that labour in thy ſervice: yet thine whom thou doſt honour with the recompence of eternall reward, are not to be equalled in number to mine which periſh. Oh what a ſad thing is it, that although Chriſt hath done, daily does and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to doe ſo much for us, yet we ſhould voluntarily leave his ſervice, whoſe yoake is ſo eaſie, and put our necks under the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Satans ſubjection, the profeſſed enemy of Chriſl, the underminer of our ſalvation, the adverſary of our ſouls eternall bliſſe. who makes himſelfe mirth at our miſery, and onely tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs in our torment let us therefore withdraw ſubjection from ſuch a vile tyrant, draw our necks out of the yoake of ſo wilfull, ſo wofull a ſlavery. Let us dead ſin in our mortall bodies, that death may have no dominion over us. So may our departure be in peace, we may have a happy end, a gloriors reſurrection, a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious acceptance, an acquitting ſentence, a crown of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to help us the better in theſe two to live, and dye the life, and death of the righteous. Be</p>
            <p n="3">3 In a continuall meditation of death.
<note n="e" place="margin">Plato.</note> Which is the life of a wiſe man, and ſurely conſidering the certainty of death, and the uncertainty of the time he wants diſcretion who doth not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently thinke upon it. Strange it is, the Devill ſhould yet foole us, after ſo long an experience with the like temptation that hee flattered our firſt parents, <hi>yee ſhall not dy,</hi> onely here the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, they did take that at once, which wee doe at ſmaller
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42199:19"/>portions, as thou ſhalt not dye this yeare, this moneth, this day: ſo, we receive in ſmaller pils, what they received in one bole, and all of us ſwallow the ſame doſe, but a ſurer word tels us, we are here of no continuance, like a poaſt that ſtayeth not a bubble, a ſmoake, a vapour, a dream, a ſhadow, wee are ſomthing, wee are nothing, wee are here, wee are gone,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pind. Pyth. Od. 8.</note> the very dreame of a ſhadow, and yet that we ſhould dote of a long ſtay here, of a truth, the life of a Chriſtian is hereafter, in the mean time, the mediation of death makes a life, it draws us neerer, and ſets us in view as it were of our life, and certainly makes a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life: for he that continually thinks he muſt die, will ſo live as he is willing to dye: he that looks upon every day that paſſes not as one of that number of his dayes, which his deſiring hope may promiſe him but as his laſt, he fits himſelfe accordingly for it, as <hi>Eumolpus,</hi> if he ſpake not better then he did.
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ego ſic ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; ubi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vixi tanquam ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum diem nunquam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diturum conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merem,</hi> Petron. Sat.</note> I have ſo every where lived, and at all times, as if I had ſpent my laſt day, never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to have been recalled, and ſurely we never ſpend a day ſo well as that which we thinke to be our laſt, thoſe three vertues, ſayes the
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>In Clim. ſca. parad. grad.</hi> 6.</note> Scholiaſt, are effects of this meditation. 1 That we are without paſſion. 2 That wee pray without intermiſſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That we keepe our ſelves unſpotted from ſin.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That we are without paſſion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 It unlinkes our love from the world, ſo tranſient, ſo uncertaine, ſo unſatisfying to the ſoule of man, ſo unworthy of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while we looke of it in a deepe conſideration of our own and its mortality, we diſcover its vanity, we conclude its no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and we loath it.</item>
               <item>2 It allayes our anger,
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hi motus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moruma t<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> haec certamina tanta pulveris exigui iactu compreſſa quieſcunt</hi> Virg. Georg. 4.</note> as the tetchy Bees which fight in troops, in their bitter conflicts, caſt up a little duſt among them, and you part them preſently, nothing ſooner cools thoſe hotter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of choler then the duſt of mortality, <hi>remember thy end, and let emnity ceaſe, Eccleſ.</hi> 28.6. that which kils them utterly would kill them inſtantly, were it well applyed; death which ſhall deſtroy them with the body, the thought of it would ſoon dead them in the body, were it ſerious. Oh how ſedate, and peaceable would we be, were we chriſtianly mortified.</item>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42199:20"/>
               <item>3 It abates the feare of death. A fore-warning is a fore-arming againſt miſeries, he that acquaints his thoughts with them before they come, is better able to endure the ſhock. As <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladius</hi> reports of an Eremite, who being neere his death was merry and cheerefull, his diſciples about him trembled, and mourning ſaid unto him: Doeſt thou ſuffer, and art nothing moved, and we but ſuffer with thee and weepe? to whom hee replyed, I am quiet, becauſe I have often walked this way by meditation, I have often dyed, ſo no new thing happens unto me.
<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Clim. ſca. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rad. grad. 6.</note> The memory of death is a daily death, and he that dies daily, dies not diſcontentedly: nothing betides him but what he hath before thought, and he is well provided for it: hee knows how to dye before he dyes, and it nought amates him.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2 It quickens our prayers, as a ſpur to our devotion, the ſoule the more it is abſtracted from the body, the neerer it draws to God, and taking heat, and warmth as it were from that fountain of light, and life, it is more active and vigorous in fervent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is a ſentinell upon the ſoule, and keepes the good man that he conſents not to any ſin. Titles of honour may court, but they ſhall not coozen him. Pleaſures of the world may tempt, but they ſhall not entangle him. Affections of the fleſh may flatter, but they ſhall not entiſe him.
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Facile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnit omnia qui ſemper co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitat ſe moritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Hier. Ep. ad Paul.</note> Hee ſlights them all, he is reſolved to perſevere in his integrity, and to preſerve himſelfe unſpotted as the ſpouſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And caſt an eye yet a little further, thinke on judgement when thou muſt give an account
<note n="m" place="margin">Luke 16.2.</note> of thy Stewardſhip. Not an evill action which thou haſt unjuſtly committed, but thou muſt anſwer for, which though thou happily haſt forgot, yet are they not ſlipt out of the divine memory. Doſt thou not watch over my ſin, <hi>My tranſgreſſion is ſealed up in a bag, and thou ſoweſt up mine iniquity, Job</hi> 14.17. When the Phariſees brought the adultereſſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed her unto my Saviour, he wrote upon the ground: he ſpeaks not, but yet he writes: ſinner obſerve: although God is ſilent, yet he writes, he ſeems to diſſemble thy ſin, yet he records it, and at laſt thoſe records ſhall be produced, and according to thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42199:20"/>things written in that booke ſhalt thou be judged. Thy idle words vaniſh not, nor dye in the aire, they are breathed out into. Yea thy vile thoughts ſhall not be ſmothered in thine own breaſt, but as they are manifeſt and known to him who tryeth the heart and reines; ſo ſhall they be filed upon thy account to anſwer for.</p>
            <p>To conclude. Thinke on the death of the righteous, who lies down in peace: thereby puts an end to his ſin, and to his miſery. Whoſe death is his birth day unto bleſſedneſſe, the day when he receives a gracious reward of his well doings: his marriage day unto Chriſt, and union with God, thinke on his laſt end. Glory and honour, and immortallity, and eternall life, the crown of righteouſneſſe, the kingdome of heaven, to be admitted to the inheritance of the Saints in glory, to be like the Angels, to ſit down on Chriſts right hand, and to reigne with him, to ſee the face of God in bliſſe for ever, and to be ſatisfied with his likeneſſe, is it poſſible theſe ſhould not affect thee? if not, let the death of the wicked affright thee, to ly down in ſorrow, and to goe into the inward chambers of death, where the grave ſhuts her mouth upon them, and have no reſt from their trouble and miſery, but it is to them a beginning of torment, weigh their end, to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Gods favour, to be ejected out of his preſence, to be given over to the tyranny of the Devill, to be tortured in hell, where the worme dyeth not, and the fire is not quenched, where they ſhall in ſoule and body in all parts endure all kinde of miſery, and theſe eternally, without any hope of reconciliation with God, or end of pains. If the thought of eternity cannot ballance thy thoughts what will? <hi>O that men were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end! Deut.</hi> 32.29. So conſider as they might eſcape the fierce anger of the Lord, in that great day to be revealed againſt offenders, for to underſtand, as to doe what is right, leſt our knowledge be our miſery, for better were it not to have known the way of righteouſneſſe, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving known to turn from the holy commandement, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. For <hi>he that knows his maſters will and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> Earneſtly endeavour after holineſſe and pray to him who is the way, the truth and the life, to eſtabliſh thee in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42199:21"/>his truth, to lead therein the right way, that tends to life.</p>
            <p>To cloſe your ears in a ſhort meditation of that which one day will cloſe all our eyes, death, the weary mans reſt, the Chriſtians comfort, the ſolace of afflicted ſouls, the greateſt bleſſing next a Saviour, conferd on ſinfull mankind, the rode of paradiſe, the ſcal of heaven, the gate of happineſſe, a haven ſecure from all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, a Phyſician to cure all diſeaſes, a reſtoring cordiall in a pill of alloes, working health and ſalvation to mankinde, a good midwife, by whoſe hands we are broughtforth into the land of the living a bleſſed day whoſe Sun ſets in glory, or happy night whoſe morning dawns in bliſſe, or bleſſed twi-light between time and eternity, bleſſed lying down, which ariſes to immortality, bleſſed ſleepe that awakes to eternity. Sweet death, may I never looke a ſquint on thee, but with an eye full of hope of that happineſſe which thou doſt uſher in, that I may as willingly lay down this body, as leave a priſon, be undreſſed of this clothing of mortality, as I would of my wearing cloaths, and commend my body to the duſt, as I would my weary bones to a bed of down. May I never ſo dote on this dirty hovell, that I would not willingly exchange it for a houſe not made with hands, or be ſo enamoured of this cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of clay, that I would not readily lapſe my leaſe unto my great Creator.</p>
            <p>In the mean time may I ſo live, that I may die to live to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that I may die while here I live, that I may live for ever, walking in that right and perfect way which leads to that door that opens to thoſe heavenly lodgings, bleſſed eternity may my thoughts loſe themſelves, while my ſoule find it ſelfe bleſſed in eternity.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <bibl>Doroth. doctr. 8.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:42199:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
